<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The consideration and iudgement, of the diuines of the Electorall Principality of Saxony, in the Vniuersitie of Wittenberge: they being required by the Vniuersitie of Iena vpon the question: whether a state of the empire ought not well to consider, whether he be bound to ayde and assist the Roman Emperour or no, in these warres of Bohemia? Faithfully translated out of the High Dutch tongue, according to the printed copy.</title>
            <author>Universität Wittenberg.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15667</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25933</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121077</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856266</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856266</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21795</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15667)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21795)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1017:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The consideration and iudgement, of the diuines of the Electorall Principality of Saxony, in the Vniuersitie of Wittenberge: they being required by the Vniuersitie of Iena vpon the question: whether a state of the empire ought not well to consider, whether he be bound to ayde and assist the Roman Emperour or no, in these warres of Bohemia? Faithfully translated out of the High Dutch tongue, according to the printed copy.</title>
                  <author>Universität Wittenberg.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>S.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D.C.XX. [1620]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>German original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Holy Roman Empire --  Politics and government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21795:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21795:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CONSIDERATION <hi>AND</hi> IVDGEMENT, Of the Diuines of the Electorall Principality of <hi>Saxony,</hi> in the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſitie of <hi>Wittenberge:</hi> they being required by the Vniuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Iena:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vpon the Queſtion:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether a State of the Empire ought not well to conſider, whether he be bound to ayde and aſſiſt the Roman Emperour or no, in theſe Warres of <hi>Bohemia?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Faithfully tranſlated out of the <hi>High Dutch</hi> Tongue, according to the printed Copy.</p>
            <p>M.D.C.XX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21795:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21795:2"/>
            <head>Whether a State of the Empire ought to ayde and aſſiſt the Roman Emperour in the Bohemian Warres.</head>
            <p>AFter the high and mighty Lord and Prince, Lord <hi>Iohn Ernestus</hi> Duke of Saxonie, Gulick, Cleue and Mont, Landgraue of Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringia, Marqueſſe of Miſnia, Earle of the Marck and of Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uensburg, Lord of Raueſtein, our gracious Lord; hath graciouſly ſent vnto vs the Doctors and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of Diuinitie in the Princely Electorall V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſity of Wittemberge, the reuerend and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Iohn Maior</hi> Superintendent, and <hi>Iohn Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hard,</hi> both Doctors and Profeſſors in Diuinity, in his Princely Graces Vniuerſitie at Iena, with gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Letters of Credence, bearing date at Weiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar the 20. of <hi>Ianuary</hi> 1620. for to ſpeake and confer with vs, concerning ſome great &amp; weighty conſiderable cauſes, and to vnderſtand our good meaning therein: So haue wee with ſubmiſſiue, dutifull, and honorable reſpect vnto his Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Grace, the 24. of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> moſt willingly, and in all things ſufficiently heard both the ſaid Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of Iena, and thereby vnderſtood in what
<pb facs="tcp:21795:3"/>reſpect his highly remembred Princely Grace, ſo earneſtly deſireth to know our opinions vpon the hereafter following Queſtions, which were in writing deliuered into our hands. And thereupon haue alſo at large in the name and feare of God, not onely diſcourſed with them <hi>pro &amp; contra,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the ſelfe-ſame day, of thoſe Queſtions they brought vnto vs; but alſo the next day following did withall, <hi>collegialiter,</hi> euen in all our ſeuerall Conuents and Meetings, ſo farre forth as was any way neceſſary, thorowly debate the ſame, agreed vpon an Anſwere, and vpon the ſore-ſaid written gracious deſire, haue alſo (for the preuenting of all miſconceiuing and doubtfulneſſe) committed the ſame vnto Paper, as it here followeth to bee read. Namely:</p>
            <p n="1">1 If the Emperour doe aſſault them, who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme and aſſure with ſolemne proteſtation, that they ſeeke not any thing elſe, then onely the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of their Freedomes, Priuiledges, and the libertie of their Religion and Conſcience, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and confirmed vnto them by ſundry Grants and Couenants; and bee therefore ſet vpon and perſecuted as Enemies.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Amongſt whom there are many good, zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and faithfull Proteſtant Chriſtians, addicted to the true Lutherane Proteſtant Religion; whoſe ſuppreſſion will be furthered, if a State ſhall ayde and aſſiſt the Emperors Maieſtie againſt them.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Who are taken and receiued into the Peace of Religion.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb facs="tcp:21795:3"/> 4 Are readie, and do offer themſelues, to make an orderly and lawfull acknowledgement therof.</p>
            <p n="5">5 With whom there haue beene ſundry eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Agreements, Vnions, and Confeſſions accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and made.</p>
            <p n="6">6 But now contrarily on the Emperours ſide, a man ſhould ioyne himſelfe with the Pope, with the Spaniards, with the Italians, and with the greateſt and bittereſt Enemies of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p n="7">7 And it is much to bee feared, that if a man ſhall helpe to ſuppreſſe and extirpate theſe Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, that the Pope will then alſo afterwards, by his Adherents and Inſtruments earneſtly ſeek the Baniſhment, yea, the vtter rooting out, and finall deſtruction of the reſt which remayne, according to the Tridentine Councels direct preſcription.</p>
            <p n="8">8 And it is alſo further to bee feared, that by ſuch actuall aſſiſtance, their own Lands and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries may bee brought into vttermoſt perill and danger.</p>
            <p n="9">9 And laſtly, thereby ſhould alſo forreine Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers be brought in, to manage &amp; ſway the whole buſineſſe; a thing directly oppoſite and contrary to the Capitulations, and fundamental! Lawes of the Empire.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſtion. </seg>
               </label> Hereupon the Queſtion now ariſeth and is, whether (the caſe ſo ſtanding) a State of the holy Romane Empire profeſſing the true Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ought not well to conſider and bee aduiſed, whether it ought or may giue actuall ayde and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance vnto the Emperours Maieſtie or no?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21795:4"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> Whereunto wee ſay, that there is euident direction and apparent information hereunto, ready at hand to bee found in Gods Word; and that out of the ſame Direction, there is ſuch a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration giuen, by the great Prophet of all Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many Doctour <hi>Luther,</hi> as that wee cannot in our conſciences either reiect it, or yet know how to better it; but find it (in regard of common equity and reaſon) to be altogether agreeable and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant vnto Gods reuealed holy Word.</p>
            <p>And although wee with other Lutherane Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines could well haue wiſhed, and euen from the bottome of our hearts, that it had not now at all beene needfull to haue had this Queſtion moued; and eſpecially that wee had beene ſpared, and not beene troubled therewith, according as we entred into the ſame very vnwillingly, and would much rather that the matter had beene elſewhere pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, and the burden thereof layd vpon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, then vpon vs: yet ſeeing it is as an high and weighty, yea, a leading <hi>Caſe of Conſcience,</hi> layd vpon our Conſciences to anſwere, as being the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers of mens Conſciences; wee would not vſe any dilatory excuſe, (as alſo it is not meete wee ſhould) albeit wee cannot otherwiſe expedite the prepoſed caſe, (<hi>De cauſa nobis aut Theologis propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſita, iuxta principia Theologica,</hi> of a cauſe propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto vs or vnto Diuines, according to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Diuinitie,) then that in ſuch an exigent, a Proteſtant State of the Empire, ought iuſtly, well to conſider and bethinke it ſelfe, whether it bee to
<pb facs="tcp:21795:4"/>giue ayde and aſſiſtance to the Emperors Maieſty or no.</p>
            <p>And firſt of all, for the better informing of mens conſciences, we neither can, nor ought now, or at any time will forbeare to remember, how that all high and low Eſtates (whether they bee of Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall or Temporall calling) ought with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and moſt diligence poſſible, to endeuour, that the Romane Emperours Honour, Reputation, Authoritie, and Maieſtie, (although he be not of our Religion) and eſpecially in this preſent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous time of Commotion, and flocking together of Souldiers, may be wholly without all impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſupported, preſerued and mayntayned in ſafetie. And that beſides the daily powring out of feruent Prayers for him, there may alſo bee giuen vnto him all due Reuerence, Obedience, Submiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Tribute, in regard that it is Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; and for that the Sonne of God was borne into the World vnder the Roman Emperour, as vnder a <hi>Monarchie,</hi> which <hi>Daniel</hi> in his Viſion conceiued, that it ſhould abide vntill the Day of the great Glory of Ieſus Chriſt, when hee ſhall come againe to iudge the Quick and the Dead and for that, the high Iuſtice of God, hath at all times ſeuerely puniſhed the Deſpiſers of Magiſtrates, as Gods, (as holy Writ cals them) and as them, by whom he in Gods ſtead ruleth and gouerneth the World; and therefore hath forbidden that any ſhould preſume to curſe the King, no not in the heart and thought, and the rich not in his Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber.
<pb facs="tcp:21795:5"/>
               <hi>For the Bird of the Ayre ſhall carrie vp the ſound of the voyce,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ettles. <hi>10.20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and that which hath wings ſhall tell the matter,</hi> as it is written in the tenth of the Preacher.</p>
            <p>And that therefore wee ought euer to giue all honour vnto, and faithfully pray not onely for the good and gentle, but alſo for the froward and wicked Kings and Princes ſet ouer vs of God; that ſo we may ſeade a quiet and peaceable life vnder them in all godlineſſe and honeſty.</p>
            <p>Now ſecondly, for ſo much as concerneth the fundamentall maine point of this our fore-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Anſwere, vnto the propounded Queſtion in caſe of Conſcience; albeit the ſame might be very largely handled, and much bee alleaged for it; yet we will now at this time let it reſt, and content our ſelues onely with that which is contayned in the Commandement of the loue of God, and the loue of our Neighbour; as vpon which two (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Chriſts owne Doctrine) dependeth the whole Law and the Prophets: And therein conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, whether the aboue-ſaid ayde and aſſiſtance will not fall out, to bee as well againſt the loue of God, as againſt the loue of our Neighbour?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> And touching the loue of God, like as the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Emperours high name and preheminence,<note place="margin">It is againſt the Ioue of God to ayde them that perſecute the Goſpell.</note> ſhall of all men in the holy Empire bee honoured without impeachment, vpon the auoyding of the heauieſt and ſeuereſt, both Diuine and Humane puniſhments: So is it neuer a whit the leſſe, but much more befitting, that alſo the Honour of the
<pb facs="tcp:21795:5"/>Almighty high God, and of his beloued Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, the Truth of his holy ſacred Word, the pure Religion, and the enlarging of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church, ſhould bee taken into conſideration and care, to the vttermoſt that all humane reaſon by aduice and action is poſſibly able to prouide for: As being the very meanes, whereby the euer-laſting ſaluation of many and innumerable ſoules, is to bee wrought and effected; the Kingdome of Heauen to be planted; and a perpetuall Church to be builded and encreaſed; by whom with all holy Angels hee ſhall bee for euermore prayſed and bleſſed, the King of all Kings, the Lord of all Lords, euen God the holy and indiuiſible Trinity bleſſed for euer.</p>
            <p>And when here it concerneth the Honour of God, and the honour of men, as whether is to bee preferred before the other; then that belongeth hereunto, which once Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> and the other Apoſtles ſaid in the like caſe, <hi>Act.</hi> 5. <hi>God must bee more obeyed then men.</hi> Wherunto alſo well agreeth Doctor <hi>Luthers</hi> Meditations, <hi>Tom.</hi> 6. at <hi>Iena</hi> in <hi>Dutch. fol.</hi> 282. in his Admonition to his beloued Countreymen of Germany, where he thus ſaith.</p>
            <p>The firſt reaſon, that thou in ſuch a caſe ſhalt not obey the Emperour, and goe on warfare with him, is, that thou (euen ſo well as the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour) haſt ſworne in thy Baptiſme, to hold and maintayne the Goſpell, and not to perſecute it, nor to fight againſt it. Now thou canſt not but know, that the Emperour is herein ſtirred vp and
<pb facs="tcp:21795:6"/>ſet on by the Pope, and is by him deceiued and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to fight againſt the Goſpell of Chriſt, ſeeing that our Doctrine was openly found at Ausburg, to be the true Goſpell of Chriſt, and agreeable to the holy Scripture. And therefore thou ſhalt thus anſwer and ſay, vpon any Summons which the Emperour, or thy Prince ſhall make; Yea honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Emperour, honoured Prince, If thou hold &amp; keepe thy Oath, and Vow made in Baptiſme; then ſhalt thou be my honoured Lord, and I will be obedient vnto thee, to go to warre whenſoeuer thou wilt. But if thou wilt not hold and keepe thy Vow in Baptiſme and Chriſtian Couenant made with Chriſt, but perſecute the ſame; then let a Knaue if he will, obey thee in my ſtead. I will not for thy ſake blaſpheme my God, and perſecute his Word, and ſo deſperately runne and caſt my ſelfe head-long with thee into the deepeſt bottome of Hell.</p>
            <p>Now this firſt reaſon comprehends in it, many other very great and fearefull reaſons. For he that ſtriueth and fighteth againſt the Goſpell, he muſt likewiſe needes fight againſt God, againſt Ieſus Chriſt, againſt the Holy Ghoſt, againſt the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Bloud of Chriſt, againſt his Death, againſt Gods Word, againſt all the Articles of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith, againſt the Sacraments; againſt all the Doctrine which is giuen, eſtabliſhed, confirmed, kept and nouriſhed by the Goſpell, as that of the Magiſtrate, and of a temporall Peace and State; &amp; briefly, againſt all the Angels and Saints, againſt
<pb facs="tcp:21795:6"/>Heauen, and againſt Earth, and all Creatures. For who ſo ſtriueth and fighteth againſt God, he muſt alſo needes fight againſt all that is Gods, or that holds with God: and what end that will haue at the laſt, thou ſhalt (though too late) finde by thy owne ouer-deare bought experience. And that which is yet worſt of all, ſuch ſtriuing and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring is done of knowledge wittingly: for men know and acknowledge, that this our Doctrine, is the Goſpell indeed; whereas the Turkes and Tartars know not that it is Gods Word. And therefore there cannot any bee ſo bad, as thou art; nor ſhall any be ſo grieuouſly puniſhed, as thou ſhalt be. For thou ſhalt bee ten thouſand times more deeply damned, then all Turkes, Tartars, Heathen and Iewes. <hi>Hactenus verba Lutheri:</hi> Hitherunto are the words of <hi>Luther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea and for ſo much as the children of Darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, who are learned Catholikes, will not ceaſſe nor be weary to reſtore again, to ſpread abroad, to propagate, &amp; to defend their Religion, with goods and bloud, with bodie and life, thereby to honour God (as they think;) which Religion of theirs not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, is not any thing elſe then the verie damned <hi>Babilon</hi> alreadie begun to fall; the very <hi>Antichriſtianiſme,</hi> and as <hi>Iames Herbran</hi> (a well experienced learned Diuine) writeth in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to his Theologicall Diſputations; <hi>Sentina &amp; cloaca Satanae, in qua omnes ſuas ſordes, abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones, impietates, &amp; idolatrias, quot quot excogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri poſſunt, ingeſsit;</hi> The very ſinke and iakes of
<pb facs="tcp:21795:7"/>Satan, whereinto he hath caſt all his filth, abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, impieties, and idolatries, that can poſſibly be deuiſed.</p>
            <p>How much more then will it become vs, as the Children of the Light, not any way to hinder, but by all meanes to propagate the ſaid holy Truth, which out of Gods vnſpeakable mercy and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, he would haue firſt commended euen from Heauen aboue an hundred yeares ſince, not vnto a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, then euen vnto vs Germanes, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially vnto vs Saxons by Doctor <hi>Luther,</hi> and from his hand vnto our faithfull hands.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As for the ſecond point, it ſtandeth herein,<note place="margin">Such ayde is againſt the loue of our Neighbour.</note> that ſuch ayde and aſſiſtance will extend it ſelfe againſt the loue of our Neighbour, if that the Lutherane States of the holy Empire, in the <hi>Caſe propounded,</hi> ſhall and will runne and ioyne with the Souldiers of the Pope of Rome, and of the King of Spaine, as the extremeſt and mortalleſt enemies of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell; againſt ſuch Proteſtant Chriſtians, as are mentioned in the propounded Queſtion, to the deſtroying and rooting out of it, and them. Yet ſo that the word Neighbour, bee not taken moſt generally, but in particular for them, who moſt earneſtly take part with vs, and hold the vnity of the Spirit, by the bond of Peace, in the onely true Faith, as the ſame commeth neereſt vnto the Propheticall and Apoſtolike Writings, contayned in the vnaltered <hi>Augsburg Confeſsion,</hi> and in the Booke of <hi>Chriſtian Concord;</hi> that haue with vs one God, and Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and one
<pb facs="tcp:21795:7"/>Lord Chriſt Ieſus; one Baptiſme, one whole vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mangled Lords Supper, in the true Body, and the true Bloud of Ieſus Chriſt; who in that reſpect are one Body with vs, and wee altogether the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of one Body: of which the Apoſtles rich and ſpirituall Exhortation is well knowne; and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſame, euery vnderſtanding man vſeth to take heed vnto himſelfe, that wittingly hee doe not with his owne hands, any hurt vnto his owne Members. How much more then, ſhould all good and religious true Chriſtians well foreſee and duly conſider Chriſt his myſticall Body, (which is the right faith full true Church;) that they perſecute and hurt it not at all, no not in any few and ſmall Members thereof? According as alſo the very ſtyle both of the holy Lords Praver, <hi>Our Father;</hi> &amp; of the holy <hi>Creed</hi> of the Apoſtles in the words, <hi>The Communion of Saints,</hi> doth euen daily put vs in minde of, and that wee Chriſtians ſhould both ſtriue and pray one with another. And who can tell for whethers Prayers ſake, our Lord hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times hitherunto bin moued, to ſtay and keepe backe many fierce incurſions, and cruell inuaſions of the Turke, and other furious inuading people? Whereunto alſo in ſome ſort the words of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle agree, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.21. <hi>&amp;c. to</hi> 27. and as it fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther followeth, ſaying: <hi>The eye cannot ſay vnto the hand, I haue no need of thee: nor againe the head to the feet, I haue no need of you: Nay much more, theſe members of the body which ſeeme to be more feeble, are neceſſary. And thoſe members of the body which
<pb facs="tcp:21795:8"/>we thinke to bee leſſe honourable, vpon thoſe wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow more aboundant honour, and our vncomely parts haue more aboundant comelineſſe. For our comely parts haue no need: But God hath tempered the body together, hauing giuen more abundant ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to that part which lacked: That there ſhould be no ſchiſme or diuiſion in the body: but that the members ſhould haue the ſame care one for another. And whether one member ſuffer, all the members ſuffer, or one member be honoured, all the members reioyce with it.</hi> And that Chriſtians in ſuch an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident for loue ſake towards their fellow Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, ſhould alſo not be diſcouraged for any incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience, yea or any perill whatſoeuer (that may thence ariſe vnto themſelues) to ſtand as one man for their brethren, againſt their enemies; Chriſt would expreſly haue vs to learne it, by that ſaying of his beloued Diſciple, 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.16. <hi>Hereby per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue we the loue of God, becauſe hee layd downe his life for vs; and we ought to lay downe our lines for the brethren.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Iohn <hi>3.17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>But who hath this Worlds goods, and ſeeth his brother hath need, and ſhutteth vp his bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of compaſsion from him, how dwelleth the loue of God in him?</hi> Whence doubtleſſe came the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the old Prouerbe: <hi>Si non pauiſti, occidiſti: ſi non defendiſti, obruiſti:</hi> If thou haſt not fed, thou haſt killed: if thou haſt not defended, thou haſt ouerthrowne and deſtroyed. The great and high God could indeed of himſelfe without others helpe, ſpeake and ſend downe hither the Word from Heauen, for the deliuerance and ſafetie of the
<pb facs="tcp:21795:8"/>afflicted and diſtreſſed Chriſtians, againſt their Enemies furie: But hee will hereby try and proue the reſt of other Chriſtians, whether they will more obey his Commandement, or the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of men. And Chriſt will amongſt other things, ſay thus alſo at the Day of Iudgement, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his true Seruants that did partake with his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens afflictions: I was perſecuted, and by force of Armes fought againſt for the Faiths ſake, and yee had then a fellow-feeling, and ſuffered with me.</p>
            <p>We will not at this time ſay any thing, whether there muſt not needs by ſuch ayding and aſſiſting, offence ariſe amongſt others, both friends and ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, when they ſhall ſee thoſe of the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith, one to ſtriue and make warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the other, &amp; that euen for matters of Faith; whence it may alſo eaſily come to paſſe, that ſome weake Chriſtians ſhall hereby bee moued and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned, though of weakneſſe, to forſake the olde Lutheran Faith, and ſo making relapſe, fall againe vnto Popery.</p>
            <p>And it is not concealed but manifeſt, how that in regard of giuing of offence in the World, the Sonne of God hath cryed out his heauy <hi>Woe;</hi> and, which is the more offenſiue and worſe, if that hereby the enemies ſhall be ſo much the more by vs ſtrengthened and hardened in their errours.</p>
            <p>Now as concerning what was the iudgement in this point, of that our great Prophet, D. <hi>Martin Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> It is recorded that Maſter <hi>Luther</hi> in the yeare 1529. vpon the Queſtion moued vnto him,
<pb facs="tcp:21795:9"/>whether a man might defend himſelfe againſt the Emperours Maieſtie, in caſe hee ſhould by force indenour to ouer-runne any man for the Goſpell ſake, anſwered generally; That no man that will be a true Chriſtian, ſhall riſe vp, or oppoſe himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Magiſtrate, whether hee doth iuſtly or vniuſtly; ſeeing that Sinnes depriue not the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate of his Office and Calling; and ſeeing alſo, that the Subiects of all Lords and Princes within the Empire, are alſo the Emperours Subiects, yea, and more then they be their Princes. Wherefore men ought to let their people and Countryes ſtand open to the Emperour, and be faithfull vnto him, euen to the hazarding of body and life; and not to hold or take part with the greedy Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morants, who vnder pretence of defending the Goſpell, will for their owne aduantage, ſet and band themſelues againſt the Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p>This his ſaying is to bee found in his 6. <hi>Tom.</hi> in <hi>Dutch,</hi> printed at <hi>Iena, ſub Anno</hi> 1533. but doth indeed belong vnto the yeare 1530. But yet after this, in his 5. <hi>Tom.</hi> in that his excellent Book, whoſe Title is; <hi>A warning to his beloued Countreymen of Germany,</hi> he ſets downe three ſtrong reaſons, and alſo proceedes ſo in amplyfying of them, that it may well make a mans haire that reades it, ſtare and ſtand vpright at the horrible lothſomneſſe or vglineſſe of Popery; and therewithall concludes: That if the Emperour ſuffer himſelfe to bee indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, to make warres for the Popes behoofe and benefit; then ſhould not any man obey him. And
<pb facs="tcp:21795:9"/>ſeeing that <hi>Treatiſe</hi> is very excellent, forcible and neceſſary; but is withall ouerlong to bee here tranſcribed and inſerted: We doe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore earneſtly intreate and deſire all well-minded and honeſt hearts, that (in regard of the dangerous times whereinto we are fallen) they would wholly reade it through out, and often ouer. And amongſt other things hee there ſheweth, that by ſuch a proceeding, men ſhall draw downe vpon themſelues, all the abominations that are done and committed in and vnder the Papacie; and ſhall as much as in them lyeth, ouer-throw and deſtroy all the excellent good, that is now reſtored and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine erected by the holy Goſpell.</p>
            <p>The like is alſo to bee read in his 7. <hi>Tom. Title of Reſistance,</hi> for the ſpace of ten leaues together; where hee diſtinguiſheth betweene the Emperour, as Emperour; and betweene the Emperour, as being ſet on and ſtirred vp by the Pope to make warre. And euen ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes in reſpect of ayde and aſſiſtance to bee giuen or not, as wee haue aboue concluded.</p>
            <p>Now if men ſhall lay all this which hath beene here prooued and alleaged, (although it be but very ſhort) on the golden ballance of their Conſcience, then will the matter it ſelfe teach them, that they are to follow the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Rule, as it is to be read in the 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14. <hi>Bee yee not vnequally yoked together.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore according to the ſame we conclude: That
<pb facs="tcp:21795:10"/>as the Caſe now ſtandeth, a Lutherane Prince is iuſtly occaſioned well to conſider, that in caſe his Imperial Maieſty be incited and ſtirred vp by the haters of Peace and Quietneſſe, to make warre againſt Gods pure Religion, then he is not bound to ayde and aſſiſt him therein. But hee is much rather bound to mediate for thoſe that be oppreſſed, by interceding, and by admoniſhing, and by beſeeching; yea and in a word, to vſe all the poſſible good meanes, that humane Reaſon can deuiſe and thinke vpon, for the procuring of their aſſured eaſe, liberty, peace and quietneſſe.</p>
            <p>And this is that which wee thought our ſelues bound in dutie, humbly to anſwere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our gracious Lord Duke <hi>Iohn Erneſtus,</hi> as vnto a right worthy Lord, and true Lutherane Prince, vpon his gracious deſire and command. And we do beſeech the moſt high God, that he will bee pleaſed for Chriſt Ieſus his ſake, ſo to enlighten his Imperiall Maieſtie by his holy Spirit, that hee may with all his heart and ſoule (for the ſaluation of his owne ſoule) tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more loue God then himſelfe; And that hee may hold and eſteeme them for godly and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Chriſtians, who doe, and will alſo more loue God then the Emperour. And likewiſe that hee would after the examples of <hi>Cyrus, Darius, Artaxerxes,</hi> carefully enquire and ſeeke out, whether that wee Lutheranes haue the right or the wrong on our ſides. And if he
<pb facs="tcp:21795:10"/>ſhall find that we haue the right, that then hee will ſo much the more (and the rather for the aduancement of Gods Honour, and the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of his owne ſoule) publiſh ſuch godly Mandates and Edicts, for the further propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating of Gods holy Truth, as did the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid three Kings; with-draw all Warre, and cauſe ſincere Peace to bee ſpread and eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; whereby alſo he may at the laſt Day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before God, as one, that had ſo much furthered and procured Righteouſneſſe as the Sunne doth lighten the Firmament. Which our good God grant, and vouchſafe graciouſly to worke and effect in him; to the onely Praiſe, Honor and Glory of his Diuine Name, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at <hi>Wittenberge</hi> 
                  <date>on the day of <hi>S. Pauls</hi> Conuerſion, being the 25. of <hi>Ianuary;</hi> in the yeare of Chriſt, 1620.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>(L. S.) Decanus Senior, and other the Doctors of the Facultie of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie, in the Vniuerſitie of Wittenberg.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
